You're listening to TIP Welcome back to the Investors podcast. Today's episode is number 837 and it's also a little anniversary because it's the 19th episode of our stock research episodes. And the last stock I pitched to you, Sean, was the local. Yeah, you tortured me with another payments company. But I got to admit, for this one, it was a brilliant business growing something like 50% plus, high returns on capital, massive cash flows.
And all that for a very reasonable price with a mid-team multiple. Well, today I have something different to talk to you with. And instead of looking at a single stock, I want to go through a couple of stocks that we covered here on the show at some point. And some of them we used to own, but then we sold them. Some we still hold, but I feel like we should give an update because it's been some time. And some we have covered here on the show, but we never owned them. In fact, I only picked out stocks that tanked a lot since we looked at them.
We'll sort of analyze why they tanked, what we all can learn from those situations, and whether those stocks are worth buying at today's prices. Well, if you enjoy laughing at our mistakes, this should be a fun one for you. Since 2014, with more than 200 million downloads, we have interviewed the world's best investors, studied deeply the principles of value investing, and uncovered many compelling investment opportunities. We focus on understanding businesses and intrinsic value.
investing accordingly and sharing everything we learn with you. This show is not investment advice. It's intended for informational and entertainment purposes only. All opinions expressed by hosts and guests are solely their own and they may have investments in the securities discussed. Now for your hosts, Sean O'Malley and Daniel Manker. In case you don't follow the Investors podcast for too long yet, on this show my co-host Kyle and I
alternate on pitching you Sean our favorite new stock ideas each week and the end goal is to basically find great businesses that we can integrate into our intrinsic value portfolio of stocks today though as you heard in the introduction. Will do something slightly different by looking back at stocks that we covered in the past and especially the ones that unfortunately turn against us and. I'm not quite sure where we want to start here today because if we first discuss the companies that we actually own or owned in the intrinsic value portfolio.
We might get into a bad mood, but if we cover them last, we end on a bad note. So I would say we just start with the companies that we used to own, but sold sort of our biggest mistakes. And then we go to the companies that we covered but wisely decided against owning. And who knows, perhaps they are more attractive at today's prices and we can discuss them looking at it from today's angle. And I want to say that on Saturday, we'll do an episode on our biggest winners too. So
Hopefully, you don't get the feeling that we have no clue what we're doing here and we can have a sober reflection on the mistakes we've made. Speaking of Saturdays, why don't you also tell the audience where they should be on Saturday, the 19th of September? It's a great point, Daniel. We hope that many of you will join us in Midtown Manhattan on that day to attend our intrinsic value conference. Obviously, the two of us will be on stage alongside Kyle as well.
We have some of the brightest minds of our mastermind community of investors that will be giving presentations. So it should be great. If you want to join us and network with a really thoughtful group of value investors, people are calling it the value investing event of the year. That's just the rumor on the street. Head to intrinsicvalueconference.com to purchase your ticket before they sell out. I'm excited already. I got to say, obviously, it's also my first time in New York City. So we have a great venue and also a lot of great people.
that I look forward to seeing again. I would be surprised if there are not a lot of people showing up that we also saw in Omaha earlier this year. But enough of that, I would say we should get into it and I want to actually start by giving another introduction to how exactly the intrinsic value portfolio works. And I think this will be particularly important today because there will be positions that we discuss, which one of us is or was more bullish than the other one. So the basics.
Basically, the intrinsic value portfolio is a shared portfolio that Sean, Kyle, and I manage. And the way we handle this is basically by a simple rule. So the portfolio is obviously a paid portfolio, since we don't give any financial advice, nor do we actually manage money. However, each of the positions owned in the portfolio has to be in the personal portfolio of at least one of us hosts, some obviously in all of our portfolios, but the main rule one of us has to own the company. So for the stocks in our intrinsic value portfolio and the ones that we discussed,
today, you can be sure that we actually lost money on them. Okay. How about we start with the most recent selling our portfolio, which would be Lululemon. And for context, the stock entered our portfolio at an average price of about 200 bucks and left it at $116 per share. I should probably be the one to take the lead on this one since it was my pitch. And I should say I still haven't fully given up on the idea that Lulu will
turn around. I think there's a good chance that looking back five years from now, especially at the current valuation, it will have looked like a pretty good entry point and will probably have been peak pessimism. But there is definitely an opportunity cost of holding a stock in your portfolio that is already down more than 40%. And that played into our rationale for why we decided to remove it from the portfolio. And so just for context,
The thesis was that you could buy this really high quality retail brand with industry leading margins, 35% returns on invested capital, 20% kegers on historical growth, and a very, very strong athleisure brand, really the pioneer of athleisure. All for what seemed to me like a very reasonable price of 15 times earnings while they were buying back stock massively and all those sorts of things.
And obviously you don't want to pay a premium for those historical growth rates, right? Just because a business has done well previously doesn't mean that it's guaranteed to continue to do well. But I believed, and to some extent still do, that Lululemon is not a brand that's just going to come and go. And if anything, it's a brand that can continue to thrive while being mainstream. And so like I said, it basically invented the athleisure style. And I thought that that might help them.
more than it seems to have, at least when you look at what's happened to the business in the last year. I gotta say, I probably have the same sort of hesitations toward fashion retail companies that you have towards payments companies. I think it's also fair to say that we both have been proven right. I mean, we will speak today also about a company that's called PayPal and that didn't do too well for us. But generally, I agree with you that Lulu might be trading higher five years from now, although I probably have lower conviction on that than you know, you have. But I think when you say that
Lulu survives the mainstream. That certainly means that they are staying cool while being worn and seen all the time. That's what a retail brand like Lulu Lemon wants to achieve. And it's basically what brands like Nike and Adidas have already achieved. And they are the exception, not the rule, I should say that. And most retail brands experience these short hikes with exceptional economics when they are still pretty niche and in the growth phase. And when they do reach the mainstream, the business looks more successful and more profitable than ever. But in reality,
the trendsetters used to wear it when it was still small, they stopped wearing it and the mainstream only takes over for so long because they go on to the next big brand when it's hype surrounding that brand. There's a hotter brand outside, right? There's not a lot of loyalty in this business and you find that out sooner or later and that could be two years, it could be three years, it could also be 10 years and that's sort of what you never know. I mean, we looked at Crocs and Crocs is a business where that seems very likely to me that at some point, this hype is sort of dying. Funnily enough though, it was so incredibly cheap last year.
that I, you know, the guy who doesn't like fashion retail still pitched it to you. And I should say that we only had a small position and we made a pretty good profit, although we might have sold too early because if you look at the price now, it is almost doubled from our price. And I think we sold it for like a 50 percent profit. Anyway, you know, you can say a lot of things about a company like Nike and they certainly have made the mistakes, but they have also proven that they are what I call mainstream resilient. So that means, you know, they can fail and they currently in the process of doing so.
But it's just much harder, at least in the long run. I generally would agree. But for me, Lulu has actually been in the mainstream for such a long time now that I do still believe it has these kind of resilient mainstream qualities. Right. Fashion is a really fast-paced business. Of course, if your collections are unpopular for a season or two, you can get in trouble quickly and then you have all this excess inventory and that can really destroy your cash pile quickly.
But things can turn around just as fast when collections go viral again. And so Lulu is definitely going through the painful process of transitioning from a rapid growth business to a more mature business, excluding maybe China. But we also don't know how durable growth in China is going to be anyways. And so they definitely have a few product releases that have fallen flat in light of more and more competition from brands like Alo and Veori in particular. And then
At the same time, you've had this dispute where the founder of the company has been openly critical of the board for some time and you've got the CEO stepping away, right, as the business starts to underperform. And then now for the rest of the year, you have interim management in place. And so that's a lot of volatility for any stock to process in one year. And from my vantage point, I still wear Lulu all the time. And I still think it's a really, really strong brand and a really high quality product.
which is why I could probably talk myself into buying it again if it gets cheap in the way that Crocs was, where we're talking about trading at like five or six times free cash flow per share. But when you have people just temporarily filling in at the management level at such a critical inflection point in the company's history without a really strong leader paving the way, it's just not a bet that I felt was appropriate for us to continue holding on to given how much had changed in the thesis from when we first invested in it.
There are many brands that go out of style for a while and then they come back many years later. I guess the problem for me is that I just have a hard time seeing that turn into a compounder at any point. And I haven't even had the time sort of anticipating when to jump on and off the bandwagon. And the idea with Lulu has been to buy a company that doesn't have these typical fashion cycles and
It's just a tough game to play. I think the time to make money on these companies is just very early on in their life cycle. I mean, our co-host Kyle has had a phenomenal run with the Ritia, for example, but you know this war, so perhaps is still the expansion phase. I guess if you would ask Kyle, would sell they still have long run left and as soon as these brands enter the mainstream, it's just a constant game of getting in and getting out of style and it's not so much about.
how old the company is, but more about how big it is. I mean, Aritzio, for example, was founded in 1984. But as far as I know, it only started really pushing internationally in the last decade. So I assume that at some point it will hit a similar block toward Lulemonus currently seeing. And apart from luxury companies, there's just very few brands that can escape that cycle for good. It is a bit different when you're talking about companies like Nike, where they're not necessarily, by definition, trying to be premium.
or luxury. But like with Eritrea and Lulu, there is this paradox of growth where the more you become mainstream, the less premium and luxury you're likely to be seen as. And so the reason I thought Lulu could perhaps be different is that for pretty much my entire teenage and adult life, it has continued to be extremely popular. So it's not like this is a brand that shot up in popularity for two years and then you bet everything on it. Since 2010, it has really been a very strong brand
nationally, at least across the US and Canada. And it did have these compounder like growth economics for 16 years or more, while they also began really gaining traction internationally. 40%, 30% year over year growth in places like China are some of the recent numbers. And so unfortunately though, the business in North America
decelerated and then declined much faster than I anticipated, admittedly. And no retail stock is going to survive this lowdown in its core market without a significant revaluation of its market multiple. So even if Lulu is a brand that still boasts industry leading sales efficiency per square foot, customer retention, returns on capital, and all these other kind of metrics, they just aren't going to be able to survive that without a massive cut to the stock price. And so
after actually resisting a handful of different brands as competitive threats throughout their rise into the mainstream and beyond, the pressure I would say from Alo and Veori and also these cheaper knockoffs on sites like Amazon has just become too much in their core markets, especially in the US. Things have just gotten really saturated in athleisure. And what really gave me pause in particular was seeing all the discounts that they were offering in recent months. And originally I had said that
If we saw Lulu rely more on discounts to drive sales, that would likely mark the end of its era as being perceived as a premium brand. And that would destroy their margins and their earnings over the following years. And that was always my big concern. And so when I had been shopping on the Lulu Lemon site recently, I really, I had to admit, I was shocked by how much apparel was on sale. And again, I've spent many years
visiting the Lululemon site for myself and for my wife and for gifts for friends and stuff like that. And it really felt like there was an extraordinary amount of stuff on sale. And then when I did some deeper digging, I did find data, I think it was from CNBC that supported the claim that Lululemon has in fact been doing an unusual amount of discounting. So it wasn't just totally anecdotal speculation and
The thing is with discounting is that it's a very attractive short-term solution because you can boost sales and clear out old inventory and it looks really good for your cash flow numbers. But the problem is that it conditions your customers to wait for discounts to shop and buy your products. And so it diminishes the brand's perceived value. It's no longer, hey, I'm willing to pay $100 for these leggings. I'm going to wait for them to sell at 70 or maybe 60 or whatever it is. And that just erodes the brand over time.
And what had made the business so special in the first place begins to fall off where again they had actually industry leading rates of full price sales, which refers to the percentage of their inventory that they would turn over without needing any discounts in the past. And as that reality has started to change, especially in the last year, that is what made me really begin to doubt the thesis. Whenever you try to figure out whether stock is a value trip or not, you sort of look for these
leading indicators, right? You know, a lot of times you see the headline numbers that they still look great, you know, revenue margins and all of that. And something that you can look at for these retail companies is discounting. How much of their inventory is getting discounted and how does it sell? And it would still, you know, not be visible in the revenue numbers, perhaps in the margin, but it doesn't have to be immediately. But you will figure out that over time, if they just keep doing that and the perceived value of the brand is going down, they will not be able to take the same amount of money for their goods and services.
As I did before, over time, you will see sales decline, you will see margin decline. And that's where you look for these sort of leading indicators. And I believe that a huge part of the problem for Lulemon at least is that they do have a management team that's not built for the future right now. It's much harder to make decisions that hurt in the short term, but benefit in the long run when the person responsible for those decisions won't be there anymore. I fully agree with that. And just to clarify again what you're referring to, Daniel, the company is currently led by Interim Co-SEOs, which
is even more complicated when you're having two short-term leaders instead of just one. After their former CEO Calvin McDonald left the company, and so in part, I'm sure that decision was due to pressure from the founder of Lululemon, Chip Wilson, who made his discontent with Lululemon very well known. And even the departure could have probably been an opportunity for a bit more optimism and maybe a new direction for the company. But it did not help things.
when Lulu announced that Heidi O'Neill from Nike would be the replacement. And so just given the massive challenges and mistakes that Nike has made in the last few years, there's definitely more exciting news to get than hearing that someone from that company is coming to rescue Lulu Lemon. And as I told you and members of our mastermind community, when I sent out an update a few months ago on our decision to sell the position, I could probably stomach a lot of this uncertainty for my
personal portfolio because of the conviction I have in the brand. And I have such a long investing time horizon that I don't mind really stomaching a lot of volatility. But it's really another thing to keep it as a holding in our intrinsic value portfolio where I'm forcing the conviction to some extent onto you and Kyle, if you don't feel as enthusiastic about the brand. And then we're also constantly comparing all the positions in our portfolio against the new stocks that are being pitched each week on the show.
Zooming out I think there's a debate here to have on how we generally make decisions for the portfolio because I think we differ from most of our listeners simply because of how many companies we deep dive per year. You look at 12 companies, Cardinal and I look at more than 30 companies each and at some point at least that's what I noticed. It simply becomes very difficult to say, company A is better than company B and company C is better than company B and I just found myself in
a sort of decision paralysis where the overload of options made it so much harder for me to pick a company that actually feel good about investing in it. Another downside of that is also that you tend to double down too much on companies where you have already made a decision. That's mostly just because you feel so good about having made a decision that you keep putting more capital into those positions because they sort of outcompeted the others. And I've done this even more in my personal portfolio then in the intrinsic value portfolio, which
I think is better balanced overall and also part of that is we're three hosts. You know, we constantly debate whether we want to hold a position, whether we want to make it bigger, whether we want to make it smaller. I do think that helps. And I'm not even sure if any of this makes sense to you if I'm just talking gibberish here. But when I reflected on my process, especially in the last few months, I certainly counted multiple of these cognitive biases and obviously not to even mention of, you know, the commitment and the consistency bias that comes from
showing your opinions and also just your pitches online for hundreds of thousands of people to see, which definitely adds some difficulty to the process. I think it makes a ton of sense. And there is for sure an anchoring bias here where it can be so hard to come to an investment decision in the first place. And there's so much work that goes into it that you tend to defer back to decisions that you previously made when things look uncertain. And so that doesn't necessarily have to be a bad thing, but it does.
complicate things when we're spending so much time looking at newer stock ideas and maybe not as much time as we should monitoring these ideas that we've already looked at previously. So that was one of my biggest lessons from this past year. And having kept an even closer eye on the discounting and inventory trends at Lulu than I did, I probably wouldn't have been able to erase the failed bet, but we definitely could have probably cut the losses sooner than we did.
Let's take a quick break and hear from today's sponsors. One part of being an investor that I don't think it's enough attention is how hard it can be to continue to improve as an investment researcher. And for myself, I often find that when I finish a great conversation with some industry expert or fund manager, my head is full of ideas. But by the time I sit down to write it all up, half of them are already gone. That's why I've been using Plod Note Pro.
It's a small device that sticks to the back of my phone and captures the conversation and hands me back a clean, searchable recap. And so the key points, the follow-ups, the things I usually want to act on, it has all of that. And that allows me to stay present in the room and set a scribbling note that I won't be able to read back later. And I notoriously have very bad handwriting. And so it's changed how I prep and how I follow up with investors. It's also built for people who take conversation seriously.
enterprise-grade security. So if you're recording calls with clients or industry contacts, that's covered too. So if you live in meetings, calls, and interviews, we'll give it a look. Go to plod.ai slash wsb and use code WSB for 10% off. That's plod.ai slash WSB code WSB. And always get consent before you record a conversation.
Curious about online trading, but haven't taken the first step yet? You're not alone. And Plus 500 futures is a great place to start. The futures markets are moving fast and with Plus 500, you can explore popular assets like oil, gold, S&P 500, Bitcoin, and more. From crypto to commodities, there's always something happening. The platform is super easy to use so you can trade on the go right from your phone. You can get started with just $100 and jump into the action.
See something interesting? Once your account is open, you can trade it in just a couple of clicks. And if you're not quite ready yet, you can practice with a free demo account. No risk, no pressure. With 20 years of experience, plus 500 makes trading more accessible than ever. Check it out at plus500.com. Trading and futures involves risks of loss and is not suitable for everyone. Not all applicants will qualify. Plus 500. It's trading with a plus.
They say every day your business is late to AI, you fall two days behind in the competition, they're only moving faster. Fortunately, there's NetSuite Next. You probably already know NetSuite, the AI-powered business suite that securely connects all your data, financials, inventory, commerce, HR, and CRM all in one source of truth trusted by over 43,000 customers. NetSuite Next is the next huge leap
because now AI is built into everything you do. It surfaces custom insights throughout your day. AI agents work alongside you on the routine stuff. And anytime you've got a question about anything, you just ask like you're talking to a colleague and I use it. And really, I think you should too. For the first time ever, you can try NetSuite next for free. If your revenue is at least in the seven figures, go to net suite dot AI slash TIP built for every industry, ready for every boardroom.
net suite.ai slash TIP. All right, back to the show. Speaking about cutting losses, let's go to our second loser that has actually just aged somewhat of a comeback, at least a small one. The average price of my personal PayPal position, which is a company that we're talking about, has been in the low to mid 60s. So I would actually be close to break even right now after the stripe and advent takeover offer. Unfortunately, I'm not break even. I sold at a significant loss.
And it also wasn't a small position for me, especially in my personal portfolio. And it's quite interesting because I think this one carries a lot of lessons, at least in my opinion. And I learned a lot personally from this investment. We sold our portfolio position after earnings in February of this year and it was only partly due to earnings and the numbers. It was also just because they fired the CEO, who was actually a big part of my thesis. And in the end, I think you can say that there were just too many red flags around the company. So to just maybe quickly recap the thesis,
because it has been quite some time since the pitch and it might also not be as straightforward as a Lulu pitch. PayPal is basically still the household name whenever it comes to payments companies. And that's sort of the baseline, right? And you see that whenever we look at how many companies have copied the PayPal model, Mercado Liberia's payment arm, for example, is commonly called the PayPal of South America for a reason. It's always good if your company name is chosen to be an example all over the world. I mean, we sometimes talk about how
Ubering is a verb in pretty much of your market in the world. But being a household name in an industry that is subject to just constant change also means you're probably quite outdated and that was certainly the case for PayPal. So when I looked at the company for the first time, pretty much exactly one year ago, I think, I thought I would look at it to sort of figure out, well, it's an outdated business that would slowly deteriorate and that's why it's cheap and thus I wouldn't make it part of our portfolio. However,
And maybe that's where the mistake started. I like the business much more than I initially thought. I mean, PayPal had a new somewhat new at least CEO who came in just one and a half to two years earlier. And he had a much more modern idea of what PayPal is supposed to be or should become. And he first made sure that the low margin business was cut and that the core of the business. So the brand that check out also be to be to some extent, but now and also Venmo, which is sort of a new abat, they go back to being profitable.
And at the same time, he grew the by now Pellator business quite fast and began building new initiatives like an ads business. And all of that seemed to work quite well. And after the cost cutting measures, revenue growth began to accelerate again, while margins also went up. There's also a lot going on with the agentic commerce side of things too, I believe. You had deals with perplexity and open AI, where PayPal became the first
payment provider to be integrated into those LLMs and all that sort of news. That was very exciting. It was exciting back then. And this also when the stock reached new multi-year highs and it actually looked like the thesis was playing out even earlier than I expected. But then we slowly but surely started to see some yellow flags. And since I want to do this episode to sort of evaluate why and when things actually went wrong, I think this is where I would start. So on paper, things still look pretty great. And perhaps I would have made
the same decision of buying paper today under the same circumstances of last year. I honestly don't really know still to this day. I think on one hand, I didn't go for a value play like paper since that and focused more on these quality compounder companies, perhaps in an earlier stage. So, you know, talk Melly or talk Delocal, which we covered just a couple of weeks ago. On the other hand, though, many of our previous value plays that we did buy for our portfolio. So, you know, I'm thinking about companies like Crocs, but also Ulta Beauty.
And even Nike, where we also made a double-digit return, they worked out quite nicely. So I'm still not quite sure whether I just totally want to turn my back on those sort of opportunities. But getting back to PayPal, between Q3 and Q4 of last year, several things made me question what exactly is going on. So the first one was the biggest one, communication. When you followed managers that were responsible for specific business units,
They were always very enthusiastic and had plenty to say. Mark Ritter, for example, was responsible for the ads business. He was very outspoken in talking about how the world thinks are going. Mark is also the one who built the highly successful ads business at another one of our portfolio holdings, Uber. Also for Amazon. He certainly knows what he's doing, but weirdly enough, the C-suite of PayPal just stopped talking about the ads business at some point.
after enthusiastically announcing it earlier and while Mark Rita was still giving pretty promising updates. That was not only the case for ads, but it was also the case for many, many of the initiatives that they just announced a couple of weeks, a couple of months earlier. And at the same time, you had a CFO who still goes on my nerves actually and who repeatedly said in interviews saying how bad the macro looked. And that was basically a tough environment for the business to operate in. And if that's the honest assessment, I think that's great.
Thanks for saying that and being honest to shareholders. But why do you agree to do what felt like half a dozen interviews back to back when you don't have to say anything about that? And mind you, most competitors back then, they didn't seem to have the same problems with the macro. And if you're the only one struggling with macro, well, perhaps it's not the macro after all. And maybe this should have been the moment to sell the position. I mean, it was still trading in the 70s to $80 range at that point. So we would have even made a nice little profit, but people were still valued.
so attractively with, you know, by back yield of, I think even back then about 10%, it just had a good Q3 earnings print and also reasonable catalysts for the future because of all those initiatives that I just felt like overlooking some of those yellow flags. And then Q4 came and not only were the numbers a negative surprise, but an even bigger negative surprise came and the CEO, Alex Chris, being fired. And so I took that as an admission that the new initiatives weren't
working out as planned. Yeah, I think that had to be the message to our shareholders. And in hindsight, it's always easy to label these yellow flags. We mentioned as red flags, but I don't know, I feel like selling could have easily been an overreaction to me when a company is as cheap as PayPal, news always skews negative rate, just like analysts estimates, for example, they should give you usually an idea of what's to come. But if you actually look at them, most of the time, they just run behind the stock price. So when it goes up, they raise their price targets and when it goes down,
they lower them and you see all sorts of negative news coming. And that's also what you saw with paper. That's what we saw with Adobe, Lululemon, all of those companies. And still, when the paper CEO got fired, it was clear that things didn't go well behind the scenes for at least a couple of months. And the management team just, I don't know, them not mentioning the initiatives anymore. You know, Macro is blamed, although competitors don't experience the same headwinds. The CFO is talking in other book than CEO. It just all looks so different from, you know, a couple of months back.
But what probably makes the PayPal case so interesting too is that the bear case has always been that even if these catalysts didn't work out, these new initiatives for the business, that would be a possibility. But still, you had a cash printing machine buying back 10% to 15% of shares per year. And that is another way you can grow earnings per share and still had some of the best assets in all of payments.
So either they would become a share cannibal and that would drive some baseline earnings per share growth or they would be bought out. And the second option is now a very real possibility. You have Stripe and the PE firm Advent put out an offer to buy PayPal for $60 per share. And at the time of recording, PayPal has already declined that offer, but that is maybe part of a normal negotiation process. So
they may still be willing to sell but only at a higher price. And considering that we could have recovered a relatively large chunk of our losses if we had held on and waited for this offer, would you say it was a mistake not to hold on to the position? Because, I mean, the idea was basically that this very scenario playing out would be the margin of safety. And that was baked into the model and it did provide a layer of safety. Yeah, I think it's a tough question. There are two ways.
or perhaps concepts to consider in my mind. So the first is the idea of opportunity cost rate. I mean, capital invested in PayPal cannot be invested in any other stock. And it sounds quite simple, but it's also consequential in investing. And since it not only makes you question whether any given stock will outperform the market and therefore present a better opportunity than just buying an index, but also whether there's another stock with maybe a similar risk profile, but a better potential return. So opportunity costs have
essentially been why we did decide to sell PayPal. And I had a clear thesis in mind when buying this stock and I sort of knew which metrics and business units met at most to me. And I had an idea of the progress that I wanted to see and that thesis slowly deteriorated and eventually it broke. You know, and while my margin of safety scenario, which you just mentioned, PayPal acquisition is now playing out, or at least it's in the process. I also knew that this would be much more of a gamble than my original thesis because as you mentioned,
People just rejected the bid value that $60 per share. So perhaps it can get much more, but perhaps Stripe will just distance itself from the deal and then you need to find a completely new buyer. And there might be one. But I think the point is this has turned into a gamble now of when and at what price PayPal will be sold. And with that uncertainty, I felt like we probably have better opportunities to allocate capital to. And just for the sake of
giving the whole picture, the argument for why you should hold on to positions like PayPal, but also Lululemon is to trust that you bought the asset at a cheap enough price that in the long run you will make your money back or make a profit one way or the other. And so it could be through M&A, it could be buybacks or it could be because the business actually turns around with new management. And so the premise to some extent would be that it's incredibly difficult to compare one stock against another and you might just be better off.
to simply try and trust your margin of safety outcome. And to be fair, what decision is the best also can depend on your personal situation, right? Daniel and I are in a position where we research dozens and dozens of businesses each year. And that means there's a high likelihood that we can find a business with better prospects and then redeploy capital at better returns. So there's very significant opportunity costs. And if you don't have the time to look at that many stocks,
it might just make sense to hold on to the position rather than diversifying into something for the sake of diversifying and maybe de-worsifying your portfolio, as they say. And then another factor is position size. In my personal portfolio, PayPal was a really, really small bet, smaller than yours for sure, Daniel. So I kind of just kept holding on to it because the stakes were a lot lower. And then I actually sold on the news of the takeover offer.
meaning I was able to recover a chunk of my losses. And that was simply dumb luck. And sometimes that's just how investing goes. Another factor that also comes to my mind is whether you still add capital to your portfolio. I mean, the portfolio we build here on the show doesn't get any new capital. So if you have 5% invested in a stock, it is quite literally always competing with new businesses that we look at because adding to them means we have to sell another current holding.
That's sort of the nature of what we do in our portfolio here in my personal one. Of course, I do add new capital every single month. So by just not adding capital to one position, while generally adding capital to others, I can change my portfolio composition quite substantially. And we can't do that with the intrinsic value portfolio. So we need to actually sell one position to add to another. And on that point, one position that kept winning all of these capital allocation was in our intrinsic value portfolio has been Adobe.
we added to our Adobe position and I had to look it up four times already. And I can also spoil that the first lesson we need to take from this is only double down when the stock is at least down 15 to 20% from our entry price because we kept buying in the range from $380 to $315, which looking back at it might have been a bit too expensive. It was probably early in hindsight and I grew that we could have done a better job at dollar cost averaging into this company.
To be fair, though, Adobe was one of our first additions to the portfolio and we started the portfolio with 100% cash and only wanted to add to companies that we covered on the show incrementally. So we had this situation where we were sitting on a lot of cash for a while in the portfolio. So there's definitely some subconscious pressure, I think, to allocate capital and not just sit on 80% cash or more for half a year or longer. And so
when a company that I considered to be very high quality kept getting cheaper, I saw that as a better opportunity to allocate capital than to invest into other mediocre businesses that we didn't have the same conviction in. And so that is what I would argue for to you. It's another one of those difficult realities of trying to manage a portfolio publicly and showcasing the entire process. You wouldn't necessarily feel the same pressure allocating capital quickly if it's just your personal account.
But of course, if you're managing money for clients, you might feel the pressure even sooner. So I think I'm a bit more bullish on Adobe than you are, Daniel. And Adobe seemed significantly undervalued to me, even when it was trading at above $300 per share. And at that time, the setup was that we were looking at a company with a price earnings ratio in the low 20s, an incredible margin profile, high returns on invested capital.
very substantial chunk of the business coming as recurring subscription revenue and then double digit revenue growth and nothing about that has changed for the record. The only thing that changed is the multiple the market is willing to give to Adobe and the narrative surrounding Adobe, right? It went from 22 times earnings to 11 times earnings and that's a great way to have the value of your position. So,
I think you actually bought in in your personal portfolio later than I did, but you've also sold most of that position. So I'm curious to hear how you think about it and whether you disagree with my thinking here, Daniel. I generally don't. I think what changed for me is looking at so many different SaaS companies and just realized that perhaps all of them belong somewhere on the two-heart pile, at least the ones that I couldn't understand because I don't have an insight as a customer, for example. And obviously we use Adobe almost on a daily basis.
but also believe that we are not the sort of company that Adobe banks on for the next 10 or 20 years. We're not, you know, this huge sort of enterprise customer that they need to sort of keep as a customer to still make, you know, the returns, their investments worth it. And also just where they have an advantage over what AI can do. I feel like a lot of the tools that we use at some point, it might be only 10 years ahead, there will probably be an AI tool. And maybe Adobe is the distribution for that, but maybe it's not. And I feel like there are so many
just unknowable things about the future that it's a more difficult bet to make than just a year or two ago. And this sort of goes back to the point of understanding what the market sees in the company and whether one has a different view on that. It's a much better business, obviously, than PayPal and probably also Lulu ever were. And compared to those two, you don't see the disruption that everybody talks about when you look at the headline numbers. I mean, you just talked about it was basically only the multiple. If you look at both Lulu's and PayPal stock chart, then you just layer the top line growth over it.
you will see there's a pretty strong correlation there for both of those companies. And that's just not the case for Adobe. Adobe has grown at about 10% per year over the last four years, while this stock has done 70% since then. Of course, you know, top line growth is not everything, but you know, studies have actually shown that revenue growth is the best predictor for where the stock will be heading in the long term. So over a 10 year time horizon, about 70 to 75% of the stock performance can be explained by revenue growth. And the main fear
Obviously with these businesses is that exactly that revenue growth will slow down materially in the future due to changes that are high brings. And when that fee exists, the multiple collapses. And that's exactly what we have seen with Adobe, as you just said. And by the way, multiples are the best predictor for stock performance if you just look at a one year performance chart. So probably that explains most of why SaaS companies this year have been going down, although technically, the headline numbers just didn't change.
I think to go on the more positive side. The bull argument for Adobe is that most of its business comes from enterprise customers that want to have full control over the creative outcome. That can only be guaranteed with Adobe tools and AI cannot do the same. So AI is always probabilistic, which we talked about a lot by now and that won't change anytime soon, if ever, honestly. And the problems that I personally have for the position, which is why I sold in the end, mainly come from two things. So first is what about all the customers
that are not Hollywood studios or big creative studios and just mention it know that the TIPs of the world and maybe also ad agencies. I don't think ad agencies have the same sort of love for the creative process and if they can use AI for a fraction of the cost that's what they will do. And then second, if it only loses the top of the funnel, which are, you know, young professionals, that will be a big hit for the company as well. So for years, that's what built the sort of skill mode.
where young professionals prefer working with Adobe since that's what they have been trained on. Then lastly, and this is a point that one of our mastermind members actually made in, I think it's a good one. You got to ask yourself whether you want to bet against AI right now in the first place. And that's the argument for me against most SaaS companies. I think there is a good argument to be made that you should just avoid owning stocks. The market is punishing because of a potential existential threat.
to either the earnings power, which then compresses the multiple or their core product, which then goes to the revenue hit risk. And especially when that thread is driven by technological innovation, and we know AI is here to stay won't stop getting better. That last point is very much inspired by historically how Buffett has looked at tech investing and.
accepting that there are these unknowns that could destroy the thesis and therefore wanting to look for one foot hurdles elsewhere. This is sort of the mindset. And yet, that said, he just invested tens of billions of dollars in Alphabet. And we know that it was Buffett now and not Abel who was calling that decision, which is interesting. And basically, he's called his negligence of tech companies a mistake.
So even Buffett is now realizing that the world has changed in important ways. And although I would say investing in Google is probably one of the safest bets on tech you can make, prices are high. But boy, I mean, what a quarter we just saw from Google again. And so anyways, I'm glad that we will be able to talk about that one in our winner episode because it's definitely more fun to revel in the successes. And we bought that one.
pretty close to the bottom and it made it our biggest position by far and it's worked out well. But looking at Adobe again, I mean, it's clearly not at the same quality caliber of Alphabet of course. And yet it still is the market leader in its industry by a very wide margin. And as you pointed out, there has not been a significant deterioration in the financials. There hasn't really been any deterioration in the financials. And obviously this can be a slow process.
as it was with newspapers back in the day, where it wasn't just immediately obvious that those would go out of business. But I still don't really see any meaningful signs of disruption yet. Despite the headline numbers that look really great, you also have these AI native revenue numbers that have triple year over year and Fireflies AI creative app is nearing $300 million in ARR. And so all that looks pretty good.
They're also fighting back on the lower end of things, too, which you highlighted as a concern a minute ago. And so in their latest earnings call, they talked about this strategic shift to focusing more on freemium users, which comes with incurring more costs in the short term because you're providing a lot of AI credits that you're not charging for.
But it also shows that they're fighting to retain users on the lower end in the longer term. So basically they had shared some guidance with Wall Street where the market was expecting them to raise prices on freemium users sooner. And they've decided to push back on that. And again, I actually see that as arguably evidence of them thinking much more longer term than making short term decisions that would help earnings next quarter of the following.
but might ultimately undermine the funnel that they've created and the flow of customers into their business. And so we talked about the alphabet comparison and I actually don't think it's a totally off comparison to make because just like how I thought alphabet as the dominant player in search was best position to integrate AI into search. And even though that wasn't a guarantor of success, it did give them a pretty competitive advantage.
I also think that we shouldn't dismiss Adobe's positioning and their ability to deploy AI tools at scale, too. They sort of have the first shot at doing so. And if they don't do it well, they'll definitely lose market share to competitors. And with the point being new technology does not have to be a threat to incumbents if they manage it well. And again, that's not guaranteed. There's lots of illustrations historically of companies that have failed.
to innovate around new technologies. But again, you do have this distribution advantage when everybody is already using your products. So if you can figure out how to bake in the newest technologies and tools into your products, then the risk of competitive disruption becomes much more minimal. That's exactly what we talked about last week of the record, right? I mean, there are these probably huge advantages. There might be the biggest advantages in the age of AI.
And that's simply distribution. And Adobe still dominates distribution in the creative space. And probably the problem is that Adobe feeds more threatened by AI, at least I would argue, than Alphabet ever has. But we could easily say that with the hindsight bias. Again, last year we bought Google and there was certainly a lot of people who told us that stupid search will die and they have no clue what they're doing in terms of AI. So it might just be the hindsight bias of me thinking that Google has not been threatened to at least the same extent as Adobe has. And one guy who
probably agree that his death cantisserie from value for capital he used to hold adobe and he sold the position and he said something that I thought quite interesting so I just wanted to quote him here he said for now Generative AI actually helps demand for adobe as the initial AI images and videos still need to be edited using the company's sophisticated software tools over the long term however we see a future where adobe is a rendered obsolete except for the very high end use cases even if the impact are many years away
we look to put our investment dollars elsewhere and we could probably debate for a while. But as an investor, you just got to make a decision based on your assessment of the future. And I don't know what will happen. And personally, I don't know anyone else with a crystal ball either. I think one last thing that I just need to get off my chest when we talk about Adobe is the management team. I talked about the mistakes I made with, you know, not acting up on the yellow flags I saw with PayPal. Now, Adobe shows a lot of them as well. I mean, the CEO left recently without any successor.
then the CFO followed just weeks later. And now you see there's major shift towards women users you just mentioned. So perhaps I'm just personally too scarred right now from that experience to overlook those things. Let me talk about personal biases, but I feel like all of that is looking somewhat odd. You know, what strikes me now that we've gone through all three of these companies is that I didn't really notice it until we set it back to back. But in each case, the management team is
really shaping changes to the thesis. Lulu pushed out its CEO in favor of interim co-ceos while the founder was publicly at war with his own company. PayPal fired their CEO and then had his CFO. That was openly saying very different things about the strategy. And then now with Adobe, you have this legendary CEO retiring with no named successor yet. And even if that's perfectly explainable,
by something as mundane as the fact that he was just getting older. He's already led the company for two decades. The fact that you have the CFO leaving weeks later really couldn't have been worse timing. And so a while ago, we did a presentation at our TIP summit in Montana about the learnings of managing this portfolio. And we talked a lot about management teams. And again, this just reinforces how important those variables are to me.
What bugs me is that in any of these cases, the trouble at the top showed up before the numbers actually took a turn for the worse. Again, keyword hindsight bias, it might have been that the business has actually performed well and then the CEO left and started to get worse after that. It might be that the CEO goes because the business is already deteriorating and he sees it while we don't. We don't know that, but what I do know is that it's difficult to react on that because you would need to find these, what I mentioned before,
alternative leading indicators to tell you in what direction the company is going. So for newspapers, such metrics were single-corp retail sales, or maybe even household market penetration versus population growth. Because for a long time, newspaper penetration actually grew alongside population. And when that correlation stopped, it just proved that younger generations were no longer becoming their customers. And it could be very far-fetched. I got to admit that. But
I don't know to some extent I see some resemblance here with Adobe's problem of getting this new generation of creatives onto its platform and then other alternative metrics to look at although getting that data will be incredibly difficult might be the divergence between total seats and actual design agency output volume. So the ratio of paid corporate seat licenses which is how Adobe makes a lot of its money to the volume of creative assets produced.
If marketing agencies use these external AI tools, you would at least get a sense of the potential future churn that you can yet see just because Adobe has a lot of these long-term contracts. But anyway, I'm just spitballing some ideas here. In the end, Adobe is still a holding. I'm conflicted on it, but I also believe it is good value, although the momentum is not in its favor. And I think we shouldn't be too affected by the price we paid for this company. I think we just got to view it from today's perspective. And if you do that,
You have company trading at a forward P of eight times. You still have phenomenal financials and many good reasons to believe it's a monopoly like position on the creative enterprise market is actually sustainable. What we know for a fact is that the market rightly so is wary of turnover at the top of companies. And another yellow flag that we haven't pointed out today, but we should discuss is the lack of insider purchases too. And perhaps because you had these
to at the top knowing that they would be leaving soon. And that's why they didn't make any insider purchases. But as the stock has gone torn apart, management has been happy to deploy the corporate treasury toward buybacks, which to some extent is reassuring. But again, they haven't been as inclined to buy shares with money from their own pocket. And so if Adobe's business does decline long term, in this case,
I probably wouldn't look back at the CEO's departure as having been the Canary in the coal mine or maybe even the CFO's departure because he does have a background in the semiconductor industry and that space is absolutely exploded thanks to AI. So it wouldn't surprise me if he just simply had some FOMO and wanted to go back to the industry that he had spent the rest of his career in. But really, the Canary in the coal mine might be the fact that there's this lack of inset or buying from the rest of the management team. That gives me some pause.
And if I get really pessimistic for a moment, I could definitely see myself pointing that out as a learning lesson in a few years from now. And so I don't know if that's thinking with the end in mind, but thinking ahead about what we might see as a mistake. And so otherwise, though, everything is so far so good with Adobe. And by definition, I do think you need to have contrarian opinions about the market to outperform the market. And that might sound like sort of a lazy defense for clinging on to
a company that we have some anchoring bias with and I wouldn't necessarily disagree with that. But I think the indicators that are driving the stock down are so speculative at the moment relative to how the actual business has been performing. I certainly wouldn't feel good about heading for the exit at this point in time. But we'll definitely continue to watch this one closely. And if we see data that materially changes our assessment of what's happening with the business.
as we saw with Lululemon, then we should definitely think about trimming or exiting the position. But for now, it definitely remains in the portfolio. Let's take a quick break and hear from today's sponsors. Curious about online trading, but haven't taken the first step yet? You're not alone. And Plus 500 futures is a great place to start. The futures markets are moving fast. And with Plus 500, you can explore popular assets like oil, gold, S&P 500, Bitcoin and more. From crypto to commodities,
There's always something happening. The platform is super easy to use so you can trade on the go right from your phone. You can get started with just $100 and jump into the action. See something interesting? Once your account is open, you can trade it in just a couple of clicks. And if you're not quite ready yet, you can practice with a free demo account. No risk, no pressure. With 20 years of experience, Plus 500 makes trading more accessible than ever, check it out at plus500.com.
Trading and futures involves risks of loss and is not suitable for everyone. Not all applicants will qualify. Plus 500. It's trading with a plus.
Most leaders are automating work. They've never actually watched happen. They know how the process is supposed to go. Someone walked them through it once. It sounded clean. But the version that runs day to day looks completely different. And nobody's doing anything wrong. That gap is bigger than most of us realize. And it means the decisions about what to fix, automate or hand to AI are running on gut, not data. That's exactly the problem that today's sponsor, Scribe, was built to fix. Scribe is a workflow AI platform trusted by
94% of the Fortune 500 and Scribe Optimize is your AI roadmap. It passively captures how your team actually works across your approved business apps, no interviews, no manual process mapping, and follows workflows wherever they go, even when they start in one tool and finish in another. The dashboard shows you what's happening and where the time is going live right now, not a report someone built last quarter.
And its top issues view doesn't just flag your biggest inefficiencies, it tells you why they're happening and gives AI-powered recommendations with estimated time savings built in. Importantly, it's a leadership visibility tool, not employee monitoring.
It only runs on apps your admin approves. User level data is anonymized by default and sensitive information is automatically redacted and never leaves your firewall. To see optimize in action, head to scribe.how.wsb and mention the investors podcast for a 30 day risk-free trial. That's S-C-R-I-B-E.how.wsb. They say every day your business is late to AI, you fall two days behind in a competition,
They're only moving faster. Fortunately, there's NetSuiteNext. You probably already know NetSuite, the AI-powered business suite that securely connects all your data, financials, inventory, commerce, HR, and CRM, all in one source of truth. Trusted by over 43,000 customers. NetSuiteNext is the next huge leap because now AI is built into everything you do. It surfaces custom insights throughout your day. AI agents work alongside you on the routine stuff.
And anytime you've got a question about anything, you just ask like you're talking to a colleague. And I use it and really I think you should too. For the first time ever, you can try NetSuite next for free. If your revenue is at least in the seven figures, go to net suite dot AI slash TIP built for every industry ready for every boardroom net suite dot AI slash TIP. All right, back to the show. We'll talk about lessons and conclusions at the end of the episode. But.
I think I can still spoil one that I just had when I did the research for this episode. And I don't know why, but it seemed to me that by covering so many companies, but especially by doing it all publicly, you feel the need to stand behind your positions way more often. And that means that all the negative news that come out that usually as an investor, you might even should just ignore, at least when it's not fundamental, we still read through them and we still have a stance on it and we still publicly defend the company also just accept that this is bad news and we might sell the company too early.
I feel like and that sort of goes to our paper point. If we do have deep dives into a company and we do that and we know everything that's important, we might just get to put more trust into our decision making and the same might go for Adobe. So I still feel very good about owning it. And sooner or later, I also in my personal portfolio will have a position again. It's more about what we mentioned today a couple of times, which is opportunity cost. I needed some capital and I sold Adobe, allocated that capital somewhere else. But over time, I will
buy into it again. Okay, but how about for change? We switched to a company where the CEO has actually doubled down massively since the stock went down instead of just leaving the boat. And we fortunately also didn't lose a single cent because we didn't invest in the company in the first place. Do you already have an idea of what company I'm talking about? Oh, I do. I do. You got to be talking about trade desk and I'm very glad we didn't buy that one. I still remember when it dropped 40%.
And literally the next trading day after we published the episode on a Sunday. And while we decided against it for what we now know were seemingly the right reasons, it's definitely fair to say that no one expected such a sharp decline. I certainly didn't imagine that it would fall 80% from its highs. I actually listened back to the episode just yesterday. And the first lesson I want to do from all of this is only just to trust your gut feeling. And even more importantly,
stay within your circle of competence. I mean, we primarily didn't start a position because we just felt like the business was too difficult to understand. To be precise, this is what you said in the episode back then. I feel like we should just put it out there. TTD is just a bit difficult for me to get comfortable with. I'll be fully honest. I was expecting for it to be easier for me to wrap my head around the trade desk after already having gone deep on Alphabet and Roku.
But AdTech is just so very messy and complicated. I just feel like the AdTech industry probably goes in the too hard pile and the trade desk as a pure play on demand side programmatic advertising. You really need to understand the digital advertising ecosystem fully and technically kind of know what's going on behind the scenes.
to appreciate what makes the trade does valuable and what can make it less competitive in the future. So this is one of those where we're having some industry experience would be very helpful. But the second learning for all of us, including everybody who currently listens to this episode is don't blindly trust valuation models. It doesn't matter what that outcome of the model is, what you need to look at are the assumptions that you made to get to the outcome. In the model from back then, we still assumed it 30 times
exit multiple because of the quality of the company and the cash for multiple today is just 10 times. So despite that, the model back then still showed that the stock was overvalued at the time. But the decision not to buy it didn't come down to what the model said. It was primarily us thinking that we don't understand the company. And again, if you will trust the valuation model, despite having a way too high of an exit multiple and still saying it's too expensive nowadays, just a couple of months later, the exit multiple
is a third of what we assumed going out five years from now. And in preparation for this episode, I did go through our master file for the portfolio and that's where we showcase our holdings and returns and have the links to all the models that we've covered for all the companies on this show previously. And one of the things I looked at was how much of a discrepancy there's been for many of the stocks we covered from over a year ago.
between our estimate of fair value and what the current stock price is. And so the only bigger difference to the downside than with trading desk, meaning where our fair value estimate was much higher than the stock price today, that was vital farms. And so that stock has come down a whole lot too. But to your point, when your model says one thing, but your gut says another, I would typically not be too cliche, say that you have to follow your gut feeling there.
If it makes you sick to your stomach to think about owning a business and you're only doing so because the financial model says that the stock is undervalued, that's really not probably going to be a very good decision to make. If you can't make a good qualitative case for owning the business, then again, it doesn't matter what the numbers can say because the numbers can change in an instant. A couple of percentage points, less growth or margin compression, all that can happen very fast. So feeling comfortable with the decision qualitatively,
To me, it's the best proxy for whether you should own a stock generally. And then you use the models to kind of help guide your entry point and try to make an informed bet on, okay, the odds of success are really in my favor with buying this stock at this price. If I'm going to hold it for the next five, 10 years or whatever it is. Comfortable in the sense of understanding the business, at least. I think there was something to say about being
uncomfortable when you make an investment decision simply because of the sentiment or the perception of the market of the business. And I think there are many investors who mentioned that the best investments were the ones where they actually felt the most uncomfortable. I think how Marks once said, if it doesn't make your stomach turn, it's probably not a great bargain. The best buyers have found precisely where the fear is the greatest and the future looks the darkest. You have to be willing to buy when doing so makes you feel physically ill. But then again, I think this is mostly
going down to public perception, not about how comfortable you feel with the understanding of the business. So another interesting point in this trade desk story here was that there were actually massive insider buys a couple of months ago by the co-founder and CEO of the company, Jeff Green. And so in March, he bought stock on the open market at $25 for almost $150 million in total. And since then, the stock has fallen another 25%.
And so it sort of complicates the signal we're pointing to with Adobe. A lack of insider buying is not guaranteed to be bad. And significant insider buying is not guaranteed to be good. But generally, though, they're pretty effective predictors. Historical studies have definitely shown that insider buys have pretty strong predictive power. And the trade desk may very well just be the exception to the rule. And perhaps we'll look at it in a year from now and maybe things will turn around.
That does happen. Carvana went from the worst performer in the S&P a few years ago to the best the following year. So it can happen, but I'm certainly not itching to start a position in the company today just because it still follows on that too hard pile. We definitely tried. I mean, since you covered it, we've been asked many, many times whether we do not want to revisit it and especially given the significantly lower prices today, whether it's not more attractive than it has been in the past.
Another lesson that I've learned from my investing journey so far is that a lack of understanding mixed with deteriorating business fundamentals, which is certainly the case here, is the worst possible combination that you could find. If I don't fully understand every aspect of a company, but I get 80% of it and I add to that a mega trend or a major positive tailwind, it can still work out quite well. But in TTD's case, you have a business where top line growth is continuously coming down. I mean, in Q1 of 2024 was 28%.
Q1 of 2026 was only 12%. Then answering the question of what that company is worth today is so much more difficult. The trade desk is likely a bargain today if we can assume that 12% top line growth is what we're getting for the next five years, assuming a similar margin. But how should I underwrite that assumption if growth more than half in just the last two years? And if you're an ad tech expert, that might be totally different for you, maybe you understand the business significantly better. I'm not saying that the trade desk is bad value right now. But for us,
It just in the two hard pile. It was there last year and it's still there today. And I've put a high confidence of saying it will most likely be there next year to even if it's at, I don't know, $5 per share. If anything, my surprise at how dramatic the sell off and the trade desk has been made me feel like I understood the business even less than I thought because it has been such a quality compounder for such a long time that I wouldn't have thought that things could go this bad this quickly.
for the stock. Anyways, that just shows probably how poorly I understand the business and that there are definitely easier hurdles for us to clear. We got to admit quality company bros did not have a good one and a half years recently. We could just keep going in that direction and talk about another business that is currently in our portfolio and it's down about 25%. That's costar group. I should say that for this company,
It's not so much about figuring out any patterns today because it hasn't spent that much time on our portfolio. So, you know, I believe the price decline is mostly just volatility and momentum was going down the entire year. It continues to go down. And yet maybe there are some things that have changed and that we should cover. So, yeah, I figured we should just, you know, talk about Coaster, which you pitched about three months ago now. And since it might be a bit less known to our audience than some of the other companies we talked about previously.
you might just want to give a quick pitch on why CoStar seemed so interesting to you. Yeah, it's still really early in the CoStar thesis. It'd be way too soon to write it off in one direction or the other. But really, the way to think about CoStar is that it's the Bloomberg terminal of commercial real estate. So it's this data business empire built over 40 years of research and physically visiting and cataloging properties. And that gives them a monopoly like grip on the comps and analytics.
that brokers and lenders and investors all depend on in this industry. And so that core data franchise carries about 50% margins and the business overall has a net cash balance sheet and then has strung together something like 60 quarters of double digit revenue growth. So it really is an impressive business. And so the controversy and the reason the stock is down so much boils down to management having plowed billions of dollars into homes.com.
which is this residential portal meant to challenge Zillow. And most people are probably familiar with Zillow if they don't know what homes.com is. But that investment has dragged the entire company's operating profits negative. And then actually it drew in an activist investor who was advising for change and Dan Loeb, who's a pretty famous investor. So the thesis is basically that the market is so fixated on the cash burn tied to homes.com that it's handing you
this crown jewel commercial monopoly data business at a discount. And for lack of a better words, the expression is throwing the baby out with the bathwater is really what it seems like has happened here with CoStar. The briefest explanation of what happened is it's a SaaS company and that might explain why it just can't catch a break right now. But I think the investments into homes.com had already slowed down when you made the pitch. So they are still burning money there.
but at a much slower pace than they used to. And I got to admit that when your first pitch goes up to me, I was a bit overwhelmed by all the different business units and some other yellow flags, which were mainly about market share numbers that sort of seemed a bit weird to me. They were quite low, although it is technically a monopoly. And then they also have very little ownership. And then the CEO also has a pretty low ownership stake. And also the fact that the CEO seems to have a history of massive spending in order to win market share. All of that didn't help, although
To his credit, it worked out in previous endeavors. But that could also be why he is just too stubborn today to see that this fight is lost if it is. I mean, even Dan Loeb, the activist investor who came in, has already left the company. And while the public statement was quite brief, I think it became clear that he just didn't believe he could have any impact on the CEO, Andy Florence, and or the direction of the company. If I were to sort of assume the perspective of co-stars CEO, I think
part of what makes giving up on this bet so hard is that Zillow is such a dislikeable company. They really have some uninspiring business practices and that have incurred lots of lawsuits for how they've run the company and lots of allegations of theft and stealing from CoStar itself. So there is a pretty bitter rivalry between the businesses. And actually Zillow has not
formed well as a company anyways. So it feels like things are really ripe for disruption where co-star should be able to come in and just take over that business. But of course, there's a massive amount of brand recognition working in Zillow's favor that makes it easier said than done. And so it does give me some pause to see somebody like Dan Loeb lose faith in the co-star thesis where he was primarily arguing to cut
spending on homes.com. And there definitely is some thought of this maybe being an ego thing where like I said, there is a pretty bitter rivalry between Andy Florence and Zillow. And it may simply boil down to not as what is the best economic decision, but a sense of pettiness and wanting to take down sort of an enemy. And so all that said, CoSar has decided to drop its net investment into homes.com.
from $850 million last year to what will be about $300 million this year. And then in 2030, it's supposed to come down another $100 million. So even if the cutback in spending was not to Dan Loeb's liking, there is a cutback occurring, which gives me confidence in not just writing off the entire business and definitely going forward, especially when the valuation stripping out spending on homes.com is so reasonable for a business with the data motes that CoStar has.
that are built literally by photographing thousands of commercial real estate buildings across North America over several decades. So we do know that the worst case scenario of them just blowing everything on homes.com is very unlikely to come to fruition as they already cut back spending. And like I said, with this data mode that they've really built one building at a time, AI can obviously not replace that.
So the other thing that Dan Loeb has criticized that maybe deserves some attention from us is Andy Florence's pay package of $40 million a year. And I think he does have a good point there. It probably didn't help their relationship though that he was suggesting that Andy makes too much money. So in the end, to me, comes down to this being a story about valuation and it's become pretty absurd how much negative value the market is ascribing to homes.com.
The entire investment cycle costs CoStar about $3 to $5 billion, depending on what you consider as solely being an investment in homes.com. And yet the market cap, however, has gone down from $40 billion to $11 billion. So it's done a lot of damage. And this is a very rough calculation, since you also have to account for the fact that CoStar traded at a premium multiple, that the market is just simply not giving to SaaS companies these days. But again, the point is that
This Homestock.com investment is not even remotely as impactful on the actual financials and prospects of the business going forward as the stock market is probably making it seem, or at least that would be my opinion. You mentioned earlier the presentation that we gave in Montana for our TIP summit. Part of that was also understanding the importance of the market's narrative about the stock or company.
I can only feel confident in my decision about a stock when I do feel like I understand what the market dislikes about the company, when I look at it, and then when I have a different opinion and have good reasons to believe that I'm right. And only then can I figure out personally whether that makes sense to me to invest into this stock. And I got to say, in this case, it's clearly homes.com, what the market is booked about. However, I think the market is also looking beyond that. And it's just generally questioning whether they will ever see any of the cash flows that CoS step reduces. So
And still, the more I looked at it, the more I felt like this is a massively mispriced opportunity. So I actually got away from my research here, feeling way more confident in it than it was just a couple of weeks and months ago. I've did some math and you just pointed out some of the points. The value that cost are lost just because of this Homestot Combat and the spend is not that massive, it's ridiculous. If you would have to give Homestot Combat negative value just to make sense for the market cap to drop that much, it would be in the tens of billions almost.
I do believe it's way more mispriced than I first thought. And I want to ask you about a week ago, you didn't seem to be worried either. So it was probably only me who needed more convincing anyway. And I think the fact that the stock is so much cheaper now, it certainly helps with that. If I were going to recommend adding more to either our Adobe or CoStar positions at current prices, both are attractive, but I would probably prefer CoStar. Oh, wow. Well, actually, then should we add to it?
I mean, if you like it more than Adobe, it should probably be at least a bigger position than 1.5%. And again, part of why it's so small is that I wanted to get more comfortable with it. And I feel like I've done that. And especially now that it's lower, I mean, again, we've lost 25% from our entry price. I got to say, I feel a lot better about the opportunity here. So what do you think about maybe pushing it up from 1.5% of the portfolio to maybe 3%? We've got the cash to do it.
So I don't see a reason not to and we are already learning some lessons from our mistakes in the past, right? With Adobe, I think we said not to double down on any positions and said we've had at least a 15 to 20% loss, which is sort of arbitrary. But the fact that we're down 25% lower and you're more comfortable with the business than when we first pitched it, yeah, that definitely would be happy to increase its weight in the portfolio. All right. Sounds like we have
even made a portfolio decision today, which I didn't intend to when I started this episode. But having that and discussed most of the companies that I wanted to go through today, how about we go to some of the learnings from this? We already mentioned some of them going through the episode, but I still think there's some stuff that we can talk about. And I think the difficult thing about investing and we learned that also in today's episode is that every investment is just different. You can point out all the yellow flags of PayPal and then you compare them to what we see with Adobe. And if the Adobe investment fails,
You can easily say that it was so obvious and we didn't learn anything from our paper on mistake. But on the other hand, you can analyze a Google investment, which was also done doing peak negativity and it turned out different. So I think it's very difficult. And that's why so few people can sustainably outperform the market. You just never know what will happen in the short term. And that's why value investors try to buy companies where even the worst case outcome is still tolerable.
I think PayPal is a pretty good example of that with this potential acquisition now and how that factors into what we thought was our margin of safety at the time. And I also wouldn't be surprised again if we saw something similar with Lulu, where if you actually held the stock for five years from today, I would not be surprised if things ended up being okay. But the question is just, are you willing to ride out those losses after things have already changed pretty dramatically?
or are you just going to hold on to something for the sake of, hey, I said I had a five-year time horizon, so now I'm absolutely going to hold on to it for five years. And maybe at the end of five years, I'll break even on it. That's not necessarily the best investment approach either. And so I don't know if it'll be an acquisition for Lululemon, probably not, but certainly there could be a shift in sentiment, business fundamentals, especially as they continue to grow in China. And then that could all change the valuation dramatically. So it's not like
you make the decision to buy or sell a company and then time just stops. These businesses continue to operate and continue to keep trading. And so you're continuously having to make subconscious and conscious decisions about owning or not owning different businesses. I think what I like most about our discussion today is that it shows a bit more how conflicted we can also be about the positions in our portfolio. Just because we own a company doesn't mean there's nothing negative we can point out. And the two of us and three of us, if we include Kyle,
can have different opinions on those companies too. I mean, we obviously know you would have never bought PayPal and I would have never bought Lulemin. But that's life when we manage a shared portfolio. The same also goes for the winning bets. I always like to mention Reddit as an example. I wasn't sold immediately and yet it turned into I think our most successful pick and it's also part of my personal portfolio. So we just learned from each other. And I think something else that I liked about this episode is that it sort of made me reflect on all the decisions that we made as investors, but also
as investors who publicly share their portfolio and their decisions. I learned that there's a huge difference between managing your personal portfolio and then also putting it out into the public. And there's so many new biases that you have to sort of tackle. And so many mistakes that you can make because of that, right? I think one of the lessons for me certainly is to be maybe a bit less active. I think we had to do that to some extent in the last year because we had to deploy so much cash. But now that we have a more or less
Finish portfolio and obviously it's never finished. It's always in process. But we have, you know, 15 to 16 positions, which is what we initially aim to. And I think having that we can just be a bit more calm about, you know, finding new companies, actually comparing them to the companies that we have. And then also when in doubt might just give a bit more credit to the companies that we own and not react to all the negative news that are coming out. So there's obviously a lot to say about PayPal and Lulu and all of those companies, but we bought it.
because we researched it for a lot of time. We also learned more about them while we own them. I think that's an underrated point that you can only understand so much about a company when you actually do the research. You learn so much more when you actually own them for a couple of months in your portfolio. You sort of understand what news are coming out, how the shareholder base is communicating to each other, how the CEO is communicating, not only in earnings calls but also in between. And I think personally not reacting too much to negative news, trusting in the process.
And also acknowledging that while we look at those companies again and again, we're building a portfolio for the long term, right? So having so much turnover in just one year also shows that we probably should sort of zoom out more often and look at what actually is changing within these companies and especially for the long term thesis. And I probably also feel that we should do more of these episodes more often, not necessarily talking about our biggest winners or biggest losers, but just revisiting investments and discussing how our thinking evolves.
Since we do that every day in the Mastermind community, it can easily feel like we are already constantly doing it, but we're not doing it on the podcast. And I feel like that's a different thing for the people who listen to us, but also for the two of us, including Kyle. I definitely think we should have more of these reflections on our investments. I'm actually working on an updated episode for Uber, which we fortunately didn't mention today. It wasn't one of our biggest losers, but it has also given up some gains.
from when we first invested in that position and yet at least personally, I'm as bullish as ever. All right. Sounds interesting. So with all of that, I would say we call it a day. I'm glad we got through this without feeling too bearish on our positions. Actually, again, came across many companies where for like, we probably look at them a bit too negatively just because of the price action and they are way better businesses than we think. But with that, I think next time again, Saturday, we'll look at the portfolio's biggest winners.
which is a bit more fun. And I would say I just ended with a quote by Peter Lynch, who said, in this business, if you're good, you write six times out of 10. You're never going to be right nine times out of 10. And I would say cheers to that and see you in the next one. Thanks for listening to TIP. Follow the Investors Podcast on your favorite podcast app and visit theinvestorspodcast.com for show notes and educational resources.
This podcast is for informational and entertainment purposes only and does not provide financial, investment, tax or legal advice. The content is impersonal and does not consider your objectives, financial situation or needs. Investing involves risk including possible loss of principle and past performance is not a guarantee of future results. Listeners should do their own research and consult a qualified professional before making any financial decisions. Nothing on this show is a recommendation or solicitation to buy or sell any security or other financial product. Hosts, guests
and the Investors' Podcast Network may hold positions in securities discussed and may change those positions at any time without notice. References to any third-party products, services, or advertisers do not constitute endorsements, and the Investors' Podcast Network is not responsible for any claims made by them. Copyright by the Investors' Podcast Network. All rights reserved.